Ivy Ledbetter Lee Papers, 1881-2003 (bulk 1915-1946): Finding Aid MC085
Public Policy Papers
- Series 5: Personal, 1889-2003; 9 boxes
  - Subseries 5G: Family Members, 1889-1935; 2 boxes
    - Lee, James W., 1894-1919; 1 box
      - Letters of Condolence, 1919; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - "A Call to American Churches", undated; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - James W. Lee II, 1927-1935; 1 box
      - Cross country trip, 1927; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Germany diary, 1933-1934; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Germany, notes and memorandum, 1933-1934; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Handwriting analysis, 1934; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Journal Paris to Prague trip, 1928; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Memorandum, 1928; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - "Motoring in Germany" radio broadcast, 1934; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 15)
      - Office matters correspondence, 1933-1935; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Ivy Lee, Jr., 1933-1934; 1 box
      - Correspondence with James W. Lee II, 1933-1934; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 17)
      - Memorandum, undated; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 18)
      - World's Fair Report, 1933; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 19)
- Series 6: Printed, 1893-1989; 8 boxes
  This series contains printed material on Ivy Lee's professional career, in addition to some printed material by or about Rev. James W. Lee. Books published by Lee are not included in the collection.
  - Subseries 6A: Articles, 1914-1989; 2 boxes
    This subseries contains any long descriptive articles from newspapers and magazines across the country written about Lee, collected by Lee or the family arranged alphabetically by author. Since Ray Heibert wrote a substantial amount of material on Lee this has been separated into its own folder, including book reviews Of Heibert's biography of Lee, Courtier to the Crowd.
    - Articles and Interviews on Ivy Lee, 1914-1989; 2 boxes
      - 1914-1934, 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 20)
      - 1935-1989, 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Articles and Book Reviews by Ray Heibert, 1964-1967; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 6B: Memorabilia, 1895-1965 October; 1 box
    The memorabilia consists of awards and citations, Lee's Emory College yearbook, and clippings from Ivy Lee day in Cedartown, Georgia (October 6, 1965). The material concerning the Pennsylvania Railroad consists of invitations, menus, railroad passes and the like.
    - Citations and Awards, 1928-1932; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Emory College Yearbook, 1895-1896; 1 box
      - 1895, 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - 1896, 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Ivy Lee Day, Cedartown GA, 1965 October; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, generally Pennsylvania Railroad, 1906-1909; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 6C: News clippings, 1893-1958; 6 boxes
    The news clippings span Lee's college days to 1958 when Nelson Rockefeller was elected governor of New York state. Lee was featured in many of these articles as the figure who changed the image of the Rockefeller family. The news clippings where collected by Lee and his family from around the country. The news clippings are smaller pieces that do not feature Lee as prominently as the articles but all contain at least a reference to Lee. The news clippings chronicle all of Lee's professional career. Some are separated into folders containing just one important topic such as Lee's appointment to the personal staff of John D. Rockefeller, Sr., or the publication of a book authored by Lee. Though an attempt has been made to remove duplicate material some may still be included especially when the source was a national wire service release.
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1893-1914; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee's appointment to Rockefeller Staff, 1914 December; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1915; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1915-1916; 6 folders (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1917-1922; 6 folders (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1922-1925; 2 folders (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
    - News clippings on "Publicity Some Things it is and is Not", 1925 April; 1 folder (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1925; 1 folder (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - News clippings, many on "U.S.S.R. a World Enigma", 1927; 1 folder (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1927-1928; 1 folder (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1929-1934; 4 folders (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee's death, 1934 November; 1 folder (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, 1935-1937; 2 folders (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
    - News clippings on Ivy Lee, Nelson Rockefeller's election, 1958; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 6D: Writings, 1905-1934; 1 box
    This subseries includes printed material other than books written by Lee. The majority of the miscellaneous articles deal with the railroads but also included are articles on American Red Cross work, public relations, Russia, and other areas of interest for Lee or his clients. "The Problem of International Propaganda" (1934) was a showcase for Lee's views on how to help promote world peace. "Publicity: Some of the Things It Is and Is Not," is a series of addresses delivered in 1924 explaining the difference between news and advertising in addition to other concerns of a public relations practitioner. Lee wrote a column entitled "American Notes of the Week" discussing United States current affairs in digest form for the Spectator an English magazine from April 1929 to July 1930. Printed writings Lee did as a journalist are included in the oversize series. Many speeches, though printed, are included in the speeches subseries.
    - Articles miscellaneous, 1905-1931; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - "The Problem of International Propaganda", 1934; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - "Public Opinion and International Relations", 1927; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - "Publicity for Public Service Corporations", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - "Publicity: Some of the Things it is and is Not", 1925; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - The Spectator "American Notes of the Week", 1929-1930; 3 folders (Box 25, Folder 9-11)
    - "The Vacant Chair at the Council Table of the World", 1922; 1 folder (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 6E: Rev. James W. Lee, 1893-1919; 1 box
    This subseries includes articles, manuscripts and news clippings concerning Rev. James W. Lee. This is a good source of information to explore the professional life of Rev. Lee. Much of the news clippings were collected in a scrapbook by Ivy Lee. Also included are various pamphlets, generally on religious matters, written by Rev. Lee.
    - News clippings miscellaneous, 1904-1919; 1 box
      - 1904-1912, 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - 1915-1919, 2 folders (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
    - News clippings, 1893-1912; 1 box
      - "Personal", 1893-1912; 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - "Memorials", 1905-1912; 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - "Political", 1901-1912; 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - "General Sermons and Speeches", 1893-1912; 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - "Travel", 1900-1912; 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Writings, undated; 1 folder (Box 26, Folder 9)
- Series 7: Ivy Lee and Associates, 1910-1961; 92 boxes
  This series includes material from the firm Ivy Lee and Associates. The bulk of this series consits of the Matter Sent Out volumes, which were bound volumes (disbound for preservation), that contain all the material that was distributed by the public relations firm. Some of the material was produced in-house, while some was produced by the client and then distributed by Ivy Lee & Associates. There is no method to ascertain what materials were produced in-house. The Matter Sent Out material spans the years 1915 through 1946, but the majority of the material runs from the early 1920s to 1946.
  - Subseries 7A: Office Matters, 1921-1961; 1 box
    This subseries contains miscellaneous materials concerning the running of Ivy Lee & Associates. In 1921 Lee explored the possibility of opening up an Advertising Agency to work in conjunction with the public relations firm. The Advisory Board file (1927) contains letters and information used to consider creating a board to meet and discuss various problems of the Lee firm. Also contained in this subseries are speeches by various members of the firm.
    The Firm History file contains bits and pieces of information concerning major changes in the firm. The Office Conference file contains important information on a new change of direction for Ivy Lee and the firm. As of January 1927 Lee planned to "divorce" himself from the public relations work of the office to devote his time to "thinking out problems of policy and helping our clients to do the things which if done will provoke a favorable public reaction." This file includes a speech by Lee to the firm addressing his reasoning behind the decision and an overview of his previous public relations work. The Notes by Staff Members includes material on public utilities, labor, and capitalism. The Office Manual of 1921 describes how business is to be properly conducted including organizational charts portraying who is in charge of which accounts and what types of letterhead are to be used in various situations.
    The subseries includes material pertaining to the firm after Lee's death, including the partnership agreement of the remaining members of the firm, signed in January of 1935, and material concerning the name change to T. J. Ross & Associates in 1961. "Public Opinion Trends" from October 1944 to March 1946 was issued occasionally by the firm offering a summary of various public opinion polls on miscellaneous topics, from elections to financial and social matters.
    - Address Books and Client Lists, undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Advertising Agency Proposal, 1921; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Advisory Board, 1927; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Audit, 1926-1927; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Audit, 1928; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Carter, Burnham (Remarks of), 1943 June 3; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Ivy Lee's Death, 1934 November; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Firm History, undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Hearing Before the Subcommittee of Committee on Interstate Commerce, 1937; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Mailing Lists, undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Name Change to T.J. Ross, 1961; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Office Conference, 1927 January; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Partners Dinner, 1934 October; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Partnership Agreement, 1935 January; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Material for "Information", undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Interoffice Memoranda, 1927-1930; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Notes on business matters by staff members, 1933; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Organization Manual, circa 1921; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Personnel Information, undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Public Opinion Trends, 1944-1946; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - "Public Relations" Correspondance, 1925; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Addresses and Articles, 1937-1946; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Sample Letters on Ivy Lee's Death, 1934 November; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - Subseries 7B: Client Files, 1910-1944; 2 boxes
    The Client Files contain material on various clients that was not sent out as public relations material. This subseries is relatively small, and does not provide adequate representation of all of Lee's clients. The Amtorg Trading Co. (a company doing business in the Soviet Union) file contains a memorandum from Lee on "the present attitude of American public sentiment toward the Russian government." Many of the files contain memoranda concerning publicity options for various companies, including Anaconda Copper Co., and the Association of Railroad Executives Files. The Colorado Fuel and Iron Co. file contains selected transcripts that make reference to Lee from the U.S. Congress, Senate, Commission on Industrial Relations hearings on publicity for the mine operators. The Eastern Presidents Conference file presents a summary of work performed for that organization. Investment Banking Memoranda is a public relations plan to improve the image of banks as a result of the depression. All the publicity material done by Lee for the New York mayoral campaign of John P. O'Brien is included in this subseries. Lee wrote many speeches and statements for the mayor to use in the campaign. The United States - French Financial News Agency was a company set up by Lee to help expedite publicity for a loan to France waiting authorization by the French government.
    - Allied Liquor, 1944; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - American Shipping Board, 1928; 1933; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 25)
    - Amtorg Trading Corporation, 1928; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - Anaconda, 1924; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - Association of Railroad Executives, 1922; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - Chandler and Company (German Loan), 1920; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - Chrysler Corporation, undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 30)
    - Chrysler, Walter Dinner, 1934; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 31)
    - The Coal and Railroad Strikes and their results (free lectures), 1922; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 32)
    - Colorado Fuel and Iron Company, 1914; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 33)
    - Cotton Textile Merchants of New York, Association of, 1927; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 34)
    - Dillon Read and Company, 1927 February-May; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - Eastern President's Conference, 1923; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 36)
    - Fosdick, Rev. Henry, 1922; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 37)
    - Hungarian Stabilization Loan Note, undated; 1 folder (Box 27, Folder 38)
    - Investment Banking Memoranda, 1934; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Macy and Company, 1933; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - New York City Mayoral Campaign, 1933; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - New York City Mayoral Speeches, 1933; 2 folders (Box 28, Folder 4-5)
    - 1932 Election, 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Paper Manufacturers, 1942 July; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Conference, 1926 April; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad, 1910; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - The Princeton Fund, 1924-1932; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Polish Loan (Banker's Trust), 1927 June; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Red Cross, circa 1917; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Rockefeller, John D. Sr., death, 1937; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Standard Oil, undated; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Transatlantic Passenger Conference, 1925 January; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - United States - France Financial News Corporation, 1921-1922; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 7C: Printed materials, 1919-1943; 2 boxes
    This subseries contains miscellaneous material printed by Ivy Lee & Associates. The researcher will find various publications issued by the firm including; Notes and Clippings, and Public Relations. These publications presented Lee's views on various matters while also highlighting concerns of many of his clients. The publications were sent to his many acquaintances and clients as a method of public relations for the firm. These publications, along with later ones in the oversize series (Information) and the memoranda, are a good way for the researcher to understand what interested Lee at any given time. Included in the miscellaneous folder are various publications written by others, such as the "Occasional Papers" series.
    The Memoranda have been organized by subject category and are an excellent source for ascertaining Lee's views on various issues. Lee made a habit of writing and printing memoranda on a wide variety of subjects. While the speeches give a good description of how Lee saw the railroad situation, many of the memoranda were written in later years and portray a greater range of subject matter including a few focusing on client concerns. Lee went as a representative of the National Automobile Chamber of Commerce to an appointment with President Franklin D. Roosevelt, where he articulated many of the concerns of the automotive industry. The other memoranda deal with a variety of issues, from financial matters to the railroads.
    - Notes and Clippings, 1919-1921; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Public Relations, 1921-1923; 3 folders (Box 28, Folder 18-20)
    - Notes and Clippings, 1928; 1 folder (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Bulgarian Settlement Loan memoranda, 1926 December; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Cassel, Prof. Gustav memoranda, 1923 August; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Cotton Industry memoranda, 1927; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Economic Issues (U.S.) memoranda, 1923; 1927; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - 1922 Elections memoranda, 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - 1926 Elections memoranda, 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - 1928 Elections memoranda, 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Europe concerning summer trip memoranda, 1934; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - European Concerns (mainly Financial) memoranda, 1923-1933; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Herbert Hoover Speech on International Debt memoranda, undated; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Hungary's Financial Position memoranda, 1934; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous printed, undated; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous memoranda, 1923-1930; undated; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - National War Fund (NY committee), 1943; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Publicity memoranda, 1923 -1924; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Railroads memoranda, 1922-1928; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Interview with) memorandum, 1933 December; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Russia, memoranda concerning, 1926-1927; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Russia, exchange of Letters concerning recognition memoranda, 1926-1927; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Sugar Interests memoranda, 1930; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Travel Notes, 1919 May; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - von Dirksen, Dr. Herbert (Interview with) memoranda, 1927 May; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 7D: Matter Sent Out (MSO), 1914-1947; 90 boxes
    This is the largest subseries and encompasses all the public relations material that Ivy Lee and Associates made available to the press and other interested individuals for its varied clients. In the letter of gift T. J. Ross states that the MSO material was "produced by him [Ivy Lee] or under his direction, as well as those representing an extension of his life's work." This series does not represent a comprehensive list of all of Lee's clients, since he may have only been a consultant and advisor for many companies and did not distribute materials to news organizations. The MSO material represents quite a variety of materials. Much of it is typed sheets of information sent to major newspapers to be printed as news and was not meant as advertising copy, although some companies do have advertising material in the collection. Many of these were composed at the last minute in relation to crises such as accidents, strikes, company buyouts, and congressional investigations. Also included are speeches distributed in full or part to area news organizations. Many of these were written by Lee, or with his help and expertise. The printed material includes annual reports, advertisements, speeches, and informational pamphlets.
    Since this subseries comprises 87 boxes explaining in detail the contents of each box would be too time consuming and tedious. For descriptive purposes I have grouped together companies doing the same type of business, some of the smaller companies and organizations are not noted at all in the description that follows. Therefore, if the researcher is only interested in Ivy Lee's work for the railroads one can read through that section. A researcher interested in one specific company should go directly to the folder listing to request boxes of interest. The researcher will also want to examine the oversize materials and photographs series to make sure there is not information on a client in these series. The first use of a company or organization name has been highlighted making it easier for the researcher to identify an area of interest. The dates given after in parentheses represent the span of years for the public relations material in the Ivy Lee Papers and not necessarily the years that the company or organization was in existence.
    Lee was a proponent of trade industry associations believing that cooperative effort would help improve production and expand markets. Many of the clients represented in this subseries were trade associations created with Lee's urging. The Cotton Textile Institute, American Petroleum Institute, the Copper and Brass Research Association, Eastern Presidents Conference, Association of Railroad Executives, Anthracite Operators, and the National Board of Fire Underwriters are among the associates represented. For descriptions of the these holdings please see the subject groupings they fall into.
    The subject groupings are:
    Miscellaneous
    Entertainment Industry
    Financial Interests
    Food Producers
    Natural Resources (including coal, petroleum, and minerals)
    Non-Profit Organizations
    Public Utilities
    Rockefeller Interests (including family information and non-profit work)
    Transportation (including railroads, subways, ships, and automobiles)
    MISCELLANEOUS
    This subseries contains the public relations output for a variety of Ivy Lee & Associates clients that do not fit into the other classifications. Description for only the larger companies has been printed. The miscellaneous descriptions are arranged in alphabetical order by company name.
    Allied Liquor Industries Inc. (1941-1946) was an organization composed of principal distillers, importers, rectifiers, and whiskey brokers founded in 1941. The aim of Allied was to support public relations activities of the liquor industry as a whole. Their main worry was to prevent the enactment of prohibition laws during war time and to help the industry cooperate with the government during war. The majority of the miscellaneous MSO material consists of speeches, minutes, press releases, polling information on prohibition, and statistical reviews of liquor sales.The printed material consists of newsclippings, and informational pamphlets. Newsletters were put out weekly to keep members up to date on issues affecting the industry such as legislation. In 1943 Allied created a Women's Bureau to promote the cause of moderation as opposed to prohibition. Women Today was put out weekly by the Women's Bureau consisting of chatty articles on current events and providing information on all subjects, not just on the liquor industry. Licensed Beverage Industries (1946) was formed by a merger of Allied and the Conference of Alcoholic Beverage Industries. This organization was a nationwide community relations organization formed "to merit and maintain favorable public opinion." The MSOs document its first public relations activity, "Clean-Up-For-Good-Will," to convince liquor retailers to maintain attractive establishments.